[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
all right I want to make sure we're all
on the same page with respect to some
very elementary
mathematics complex
numbers just one important
concept so I just want to go through
them very quickly extremely quickly a
complex number has a real part and an
imaginary part and you can plot it on a
two-dimensional surface the
two-dimensional
surface horizontal axis represents the
real part of the function not the
function just the real part of the
number and the imaginary part of the
number is plotted on the vertical axis
and a point on this plane is an
imaginary
number uh if this is
X and the height is
y then the complex number is z which is
X Plus i
y okay uh we could also represent it
another way we can represent it in terms
of a distance which we can call R and an
angle that we can call
Theta okay and now just from elementary
trigonometry the distance X is R times
the cosine of
theta so that's X is R cosine
Theta and Y is R * R * sin Theta so I *
R sin
Theta or in other words we can take the
r out out of it Factor the r out and
write that Z is equal to R * cine Theta
+ I sin Theta the comb
cosine theta plus I sin Theta is called
E to the I
Theta e to the power I
Theta so know that definition e to the I
Theta is cosine theta plus I sin
Theta the reason we call it e to the I
Theta is because it satisfies certain
rules of exponentials the rules of
exponentials is that when you multiply
exponentials you add the
exponents all right e to 3 * e to 5 is e
to 8 3 and 5 is
8 you can check using Elementary
trigonometry that if you have two angles
Theta and F uh and you write e to the I
which is cosine f plus I sin 5 and
multiply them you get something with a
real and an imaginary part the real part
is cine Theta cosine 5 minus sin Theta *
sin 5 remember I * I is minus I that's
minus one so if you multiply these two
what you get is
cosine Theta well I'll tell you what you
get let's let's simplify it you get
cosine Theta cosine Fus sin Theta sin 5
anybody know what that
is right cosine of Theta + f that's
sorry that's a high school trigonometry
formula the cosine of the sum of two
angles cosine cosine minus sin * s and
then plus the imaginary part the
imaginary part is cosine Theta sin 5
plus cosine 5 * sin Theta and that's
just s of theta + 5 and by
definition if e to the I Theta is cosine
plus I sin then this is just cosine then
this is just e to the I Theta + f so
from elementary trigonometry we discover
that this combination cosine theta plus
I sin Theta has all of the properties of
the exponential of I Theta now all of
trigonometry anything you ever wanted to
remember about trigonometry couldn't
remember is all stored in this formula
for example if you couldn't remember
what the cosine of the sum of two angles
is all you need to do is multiply e to
the I Theta * e to the I in this form
and you'll discover that cosine Theta +
5 is cosine Theta cosine 5us sin Theta
sin 5 so all of trigonometry I don't
know why they take a year to teach
trigonometry in high school and then at
the end of it they come here to Stanford
and they don't know this formula
okay
uh another fact let's uh we could check
this uh in two ways we could just use
the formula for adding for multiplying
exponentials e to the I Theta all right
first of all there's e to the I Theta
that's cosine theta plus I sin Theta
remember what the complex conjugate of a
thing is the complex
conjugate is just the same number
except with the imaginary part changing
sign so it's the reflected number in the
lower half plane if the numberb is in
the upper half plane then it's reflected
into the lower half plane or vice
versa um the complex conjugate of e to
the I Theta is cosine Theta minus I sin
Theta okay but that's the same thing
that's e to the minus I Theta that's the
same thing
as e it's cosine
Theta minus I sin
Theta and if you remember that the s
that minus the S of theta is the same
thing as s of minus Theta then you
realize this is just e to the minus I
Theta so the complex conjugate of e to
the I Theta you just get by changing the
I the sign of the I here and what
happens if you multiply these two
you get one I think of it as changing
the sign of Thea because that's what
happens when you rotate the count
clockwise Direction instead of the
counterclockwise direction right
true this is true I don't know if
everybody caught that but if you
multiply e to the I Theta * e to the
minus I
Theta you get one all right so the class
of
numbers which are the class of complex
numbers which are of the form e to the I
Theta are numbers which have the special
property that when they multiplied by
the complex conjugate the result is one
and there's another way to say that now
the other way to say it is that X2 + y^2
is equal to
1 the the class of numbers for which X2
+ y^2 remember a number times its
complex conjugate is just the sums of
the squares of the real and imaginary
part
and so the numbers which have the form e
to the I Theta let's specialize to those
are numbers for which X2 + y^2 is equal
to 1 in other words they're numbers on
the unit
circle on the circle of radius
one they're simply called numbers I
don't know what to call them unitary
numbers
numbers uh of the form e to the I Theta
you can call them unitary numbers and
they're numbers that have the property
that they lie on the unit circle and
they times their complex conjugate is
exactly equal to one every complex
number is a unitary
number times a real number a real
positive number and the real positive
number is just the
radius uh or the distance to that point
on the complex plane all right that's uh
that's all we need to know that's all
there is to complex numbers there is
nothing else
nothing else I can think of off
hand and I want to make sure everybody
knows ah the other word for a number
which is of the form e to the I
Theta is that it's called a pure
phase the angle in here is called the
phase angle the phase and the radius is
called the modulus I guess the modulus
means the size of it so a number which
has no R in front of it or R is one
number on the unit circle is called a
pure phase so just a
phase so when
I swallow the I swallowed the chocolate
chip
wrong when I refer to a pure phase that
means a number cosine theta plus I sin
Theta okay
now see
all right now the postulates of quantum
mechanics we want to now today go
through the basic postulates of quantum
mechanics now what quantum mechanics is
is it's a calculus for calculating
probabilities
uh after a while you get some intuition
for and maybe you get some pictures of
what's going on but think of it as a
calculus in other words a calculational
procedure for calculating probabilities
probabilities of what probabilities for
different measurements different values
of measurements the things you measure
are called
observables you prepare systems in
certain States not in California or New
York but in certain configurations that
are called States and those states are
labeled by or described by vectors in a
complex Vector space we've called them
alpha or a I guess we call them
a you can add them you can subtract them
you can multiply them by numbers and
they form a complex Vector space number
one number
two uh we normalize them in fact in the
particular simple case that we studied
which was the twole system
we could describe this as Alpha time the
upstate for example plus beta time the
down state where Alpha and beta are
complex
numbers uh the coefficients
here are such that Alpha star
Alpha and beta star beta are the
probabilities that if you were to
measure up or down you would measure up
with probability Alpha star Alpha down
with beta star Beta And
so just to make the probability Al
together equal to one we require that uh
that the
coefficients are such that the sums of
the squares or the sums of the I'll call
it's just a square it's the square of
the uh is just equal to one all right
there's another way to rewrite the same
equation it's that the inner product of
a
a real state with itself is just equal
to one that is equal to Alpha star Alpha
plus beta star Beta And so this is the
abstract way of writing that the total
probability adds up to
one so States state vectors are
normalized this is called
normalized normalized means the length
of the vector in some sense is equal to
one and altogether the sums of the
probabilities are one
that's the basic posture the
states uh this is an the example of the
two-dimensional space of States
two-dimensional doesn't mean the world
is two-dimensional it just means that
there are two independent possibilities
up and down heads and
tails we discussed how you might measure
whether a spin was up or down by putting
it into a magnetic field and seeing if
it emits a photon or not so given
uh an arbitrary state of electron we can
measure its spin if it gives off a
photon then we say it's down I
guess and if it doesn't give off a
photon then we say it's up and the
relative probabilities or the
probabilities for the two are just the
coefficients here now those
probabilities of course do not
completely determine the complex numbers
here why
not well if I multiply any complex
number number by a pure
phase it doesn't change its
magnitude right if I take a complex
number and I multiply it by e to the I
Theta where Theta is any
angle I get a new number whose magnitude
whose Alpha star Alpha is exactly the
same as the original starting number and
so knowing the probabilities is not
enough to complete completely determine
what these coefficients are so there's
more information in these coefficients
than just the probabilities and we're
going to find out what that additional
information
is but for the
moment this
is and of course if there's more than
two possibilities up down and sideways
or up down and um and a chocolate chip
then we add another one gamma
chw chip
whatever those areal those are
orthonormal vectors and we're going to
right right and we represented them in a
particular basis the basis of up and
down we represented them let's just uh
we represented them
as up was just one
Zer and down
is equal to
01 they're orthogonal to each
other they're normalized both of them
the sums of the squares of each
individual one is one so they're called
orthonormal vectors orthogonal and
normal if we if we have a higher
dimensional Vector space with more
possibilities chocolate chip then we
might have three vectors Al together
01 they are still orthogonal and
normalized this this uh this zero should
go here
down up and down in the space of States
not
in we're going to we're going to have to
remember the difference between these
vectors these abstract vectors which
represent States and vectors in real
space because that's going to come up
today
pointers these are Pointers they're not
vectors and we'll label them slightly
differently all right
now what about the quantities that you
measure they are called observables
they're the things that you
measure and by assumption you you there
may be more than one thing that you can
measure about a
system and you can always reduce them to
real numbers the results of a
measurement are always always a
collection of real
numbers uh you may combine them together
for example into a complex number but
the results of real measurements um you
know pointers on a dial or whatever are
real numbers and so
observables are things which when you
measure them among other things you get
real numbers as a result they are
represented by matrix or operators
strictly speaking they're represented by
linear
operators which you can take to just
being matrices for our
purpose but a special class of matrices
the hermiss
matrices Herm Mission h e r m i t a n
her mission for hermite and hermite was
a
mathematician Herm Mission matrices and
to Define them let's first Define a
couple of Concepts about matrices
first of all there's the concept of the
transpose of a
matrix the transpose of a
matrix you have diagonal elements and
off diagonal elements and there's no
reason why it has to be 2 by two let's
take it to be
3x3 uh there's M11
M22
m33 and then there's the off diagonal
elements let's just put one of them over
here here's um
M12 and here's M21 and so forth and
there other ones
other they're all there the transpose of
a matrix is
just you act on The Matrix to
Interchange rows and columns all it
means is you reflect it about the
diagonal you just imagine it's written
on a piece of paper and you turn over
the piece of paper so so that
M12 replaces M21 and so
forth the way to write that the
transpose the transpose is just written
by putting a t up here and it's just the
diagonal elements are
unchanged but the off diagonal elements
M12 becomes
M21 and M12 they just
interchange and likewise over here and
so
forth okay that's called the
transpose we can write that in the form
the transpose Matrix we can call IJ the
J element of it is just the j i element
of the original Matrix interchange of I
and J of rows and columns is called
transpose the next constract
is the hermiss conjugate I'll write it
out hermiss conjugate and it's a kind
of complex conjugation but complex
conjugation for matrices Herm Mission
conjugate and it involves two
operations the first is to
transpose and then the complex
conjugate and it's represented by a
dagger
it's represented by a
dagger the comp and it's represented by
first of all
transposing but then complex conjugating
everything all the elements the diagonal
elements as well as the off diagonal
elements and we write it by saying that
the Herm mission
conjugate the dagger of a
matrix is you interchange rows and
columns and then you complex
conjugate all right so let's do an
example here's an
example 4 + 2
I uh 7 -
I uh 6 + 4 I and 9 - 2 I
all right what's the what's the dagger
the uh the hermiss conjugate of that
Matrix
well the diagonal elements they don't
move when you transpose transposing a
diagonal element stays in the same place
but we have to complex conjugated so we
get 4 minus 2
I now the element up here first we have
to
transpose what was this four four minus
2 I yeah okay we have to transpose which
means we put we
interchange rows and
columns and then complex conjugate so
then we get 4 + 2 I up
here we put this one complex conjugated
this one complex conjugated goes down
here 6 minus 4
I and the diagonal matrix element stays
where it is but it gets complex
conjugated 7 plus I all right so that's
the that's the that's the idea of
uh Herm Mission conjugation flip the
rows and columns and
then
uh and then complex
conjugate a Herm Mission Matrix well
first let's talk about symmetric
matrices symmetric matrices let's just
go back to the idea of transpose without
the complex
conjugation just the
transpose a symmetric Matrix is one that
is equal to its own transpose in other
words when you transpose it you get back
the same thing in order for that to be
the case all that you need is that the
elements the reflected elements are the
same as each other so it would say that
M to1 has to be equal to
M12 put the same M21 here that's the
idea of a symmetric Matrix and it just
is exactly what it says it's sort of
symmetric with respect to flipping it or
to reflecting it about the main
diagonal a symmetric Matrix
satisfies M J equals
mji that's a symmetric Matrix very
simple concept A Herm Mission Matrix is
a little more complicated
and what it says a Herm Mission Matrix
is a matrix which is equal to its own
Herm Mission conjugate so if you have a
matrix and you Herm Mission conjugate it
if it is equal to the original matrix
it's called Herm Mission it's just
called Herm Mission that's the
definition of a Herm Mission Matrix
let's write a Herm Mission Matrix down
write the formula for it
yes yes
yes there's the formula for it right
here m j is MJ complex
conjugate all right
now say it
again I think it's written correctly m j
is MI mji conjugate
it's
correct what it says first of all is
that the diagonal elements are real for
example this says if you interchange I
and J on a diagonal element you just get
the same diagonal element so it says
that M11 is equal to M11
star that means that M11 is real so real
numbers on the
diagonal not all the same real number I
mean I just wrote real real real real
meaning any real number in any one of
these
places and then on the off diagonal
elements over here let's suppose that
this off diagonal element over here is
z the complex number
Z then the reflected off diagonal
element has to be the complex conjugate
then it's called Herm
Mission
so two
7 uh 1 + I and 1 minus i is her Mission
real elements on the diagonal and
complex conjugates when you
reflect this is a kind of reality
property a thing being its own complex
conjugate for a number is says that it's
real for a matrix the concept of reality
is not that the Matrix elements are all
real not that each Matrix element
separately is its own complex conjugate
but each Matrix element is the complex
conjugate of the reflected Matrix
element we'll find out we're going to
see very shortly why this is a good
definition okay I'm going to write down
some theorems these are your homework to
prove they're very very
simple but just
uh they don't have names because they're
too simple
very Elementary
theorems first of all if you take two
vectors A and B and you take the inner
product of a with
B now remember when you form the row
Vector B you use the complex conjugate
elements this is equal
to B Star Bar star one B Star 2 complex
conjugate time A1
A2 the first theorem is that if you
interchange A and
B that will put the A's here and the B's
here what do you
get is this
correct
no complex
conjugate the way to think of it is that
the row Vector is like the complex
conjugate of a certain column vector and
if you interchange if you interchange uh
the order of these you're taking the
complex conjugate of B and the complex
conjugate of a and if you multiply
complex conjugates it's just complex
conjugates so the first the first
Elementary theorem to check is that the
inner product of B with a is the complex
conjugate of the inner product of a with
B now
that's it's extremely Elementary anybody
who's seen it of course is very familiar
with
it next statement now this one is less
obvious take any Matrix her Mission or
not her
Mission and
I'll
and all right now this is an operation
that I haven't defined yet but I'm going
to Define it for you right now it's very
simple you have a matrix M and you
multiply it by a that gives you a new
Vector this is a new
vector and you take that new vector and
you take the inner product with
B you can work out what this is in terms
of the Matrix elements of M and the
entries that go into a and b it's a very
definite expression first multiply the
matrix by a or multiply a by The Matrix
you'll be left over with a new Vector
that you can call a prime and you take
its in APR with
B this is related to but not equal
to I'm going to write equal but then
we're going to change it interchange
everything a put a on the left that's
kind of the complex conjugate of a put B
on the
right and put the hermiss conjugate of
M everybody has been complex conjugated
and all rows and columns have been
interchanged
when you interchange A and B you're
interchanging a column Vector with a row
vector and you're complex conjugating
the same for M when you take its Herm
Mission conjugate you interchange rows
and columns and you and you complex
conjugate this is a number
incidentally this quantity is a number a
complex number in
general M on a gives you a vector the
inner product of a vector with another
Vector is a number
number okay a simple number it's not a
matrix it's not a vector it's just a
number this equation is not
right what do I have to do to it complex
conjugated I've complex conjugated a
I've complex conjugated B and I've
complex conjugated M so I have to take
the whole thing and complex
conjugated so that's a um
a simple fact
about about
um uh complex conjugation of matrices
and vectors but let's suppose that our
Matrix is her Mission let's suppose that
the Matrix in question is her Mission if
it is her Mission I can eras I can erase
this uh conjugation sign here if it's
Herm Mission it's equal to its own Herm
mission conjugate definition of Herm
Mission so for a Herm Mission Matrix and
from now on let's think about Herm
Mission matrices for Herm Mission
matrices for her Mission
matrices the this is called a matrix
element this is called the ba Matrix
element of M the ba Matrix element of M
is the same as the a mat Matrix element
of M complex
conjugated now one last thing that will
make the point for you if a and b happen
to be the same Vector if a and b happen
to be the same Vector so now let's let b
equal
a let b equal
a let b equal a
look what this
says it says that the Matrix element of
M
evaluated between sandwiched between two
states which are the same the same state
a on both sides is equal to its own
complex conjugate what does that say
about
AMA that it's
real so if you have a Herm Mission
Matrix this was the theorem that I was
going to ask you to prove but I just
proved
it if you have a a permission
Matrix
then we should give this object a name
it's called the expectation value why
it's the expectation value will become
or what that has what it has to do with
anybody's
expectations is something else it just
has a name it's the expectation value of
m in the state a now remember just keep
in
mind the way we're going to be
describing States is through vectors the
way we describe observables is through
matrices so you can think of this
basically as the average value of
M when the state of the system is
a yeah
yeah sure of course comes from direct
yeah all right so what do we learn we
learn that if we have a Herm Mission
Matrix its expectation value is
real well we haven't gone through the
details yet but that sounds like a good
thing if we have a uh an observable
which is represented in which when you
measure it always gives you a real
number then obvious ly its average value
should be real and that's what we find
that for a Herm Mission
Matrix its expectation value in a given
state is real that's what makes the Herm
Mission matrices special and what's Mak
what makes the Herm Mission matrices
natural candidates to have something to
do with observable quantities because
their expectation values in any state
doesn't have to uh there are many many
states any one of them will satisfy this
okay any questions up till
now anything that you really measure is
always a number now you can you can
decide to say uh I will describe points
locations of particles on the surface of
the Earth by giving a complex number
I'll give you an address in Manhattan by
giving you a you know Manhattan is lay
down on the grid I'll give you a complex
number uh but uh you don't have to do
that you can represent any observable
quantity as a collection of real numbers
always you can always represent uh the
results of a series of an experiment by
a series of real numbers right and those
real numbers are called observables when
they're when they're complex when you
add them together in complex
combinations just because of the
technical historical definition we don't
call it an
observable uh the observables are the
collection of real numbers yeah to the
same question what's a good way to think
about measur numbers when they show up
in physical formulas like is it like
these things exist but they're not
observable but then how do we know that
they exist if they're not observable
sort
of uh I think I I think there's a better
I I think the question that you really
want to ask is why do we get why do we
have to use complex numbers in quantum
mechanics that's I think what you really
want to ask why is it that we're driven
to complex numbers this will become
clear but it has to do with time and
reversibility
and we're not there yet we're not ready
for it we could have thought about doing
quantum mechanics with all real numbers
and never having gotten complex numbers
we missed some very important things as
you will see as you will find out but uh
but let's let's write down the
postulates examine their consequences
and then I will tell you what would go
wrong if you restricted yourself to real
numbers all right it would have to do in
particular
um with the evolution of State vectors
what we have not talked about at all is
how things change with time and it
really has to do with how things change
with time that uh where that I comes
from so hold on hold on to the question
and uh and it'll come back again I I
realized it's a different question than
you asked but uh but uh I think it's the
right question why what complex numbers
are is they just a mathematical
formalism for describing pairs of real
numbers in certain ways okay what uh why
are we driven to use them in Quant
mechanics it has to do with time
Evolution so we'll come to
it
um good all right we're still doing
mathematics we cannot do this subject
without mathematics
I mean I can fake it I can tell you lots
of stuff about quantum mechanics and
give you all sorts of mystical
experiences about entanglement and uh
and when you walk out of here you will
know no more about entanglement than you
knew when you walked in but you'll have
this fuzzy uh feeling about it and
you'll say oh isn't it wonderful and
it's mysterious but you won't have any
idea what it is so uh so if we want to
really do it honestly we are forced to
do this
mathematics right
right we want to do better than that we
want to really do it
right in the simple in the simplest
possible context I mean I'm giving you
the simplest possible context to discuss
quantum mechanics basically the
two-level system and then we'll do two
two-level systems and then we'll talk
about the entanglement of two two level
systems and we'll understand it in some
detail and
uh and you'll know what the words really
mean all right the next concept and it's
basically the last mathematical concept
that we'll need for today and possibly
for quite a while is the concept of igen
values and igen
vectors particularly igen values and
igen vectors of Herm Mission
operators so what is an igen value and
an igen
Vector well if I give you a matrix or an
operator Matrix or an operator
M the if it's a in general there may or
may not be certain vectors that when I
apply the Matrix to them don't change
the vector except to multiply it by a
number okay in other words there may or
may not
be and typically there will be and in
fact in the case of Herm Mission
matrices there always are certain
vectors we take a
matrix there will exist certain
vectors which have the property not
every Vector there will exist certain
vectors that are that are associated
with that Matrix which are called its
igen
vectors which have the
property that you just multiply by a
number the number depends on the
vector I will give you a very very
simple example right
now supposing we have a diagonal matrix
in general it will be called an igen
value and an igen Vector even if it's
complex but if m is a Herm Mission
Matrix then it follows that Lambda is
real let's prove that let's suppose we
have a Herm Mission Matrix we have found
an igen vector and an igen value let's
see what we learn by taking the inner
product of this equation with a itself
we have m a a and multiplying the
equation on the left by a Lambda is a
number it just comes on the
outside
AA now if you go back in your notes
about 5 and a half minutes we remember
that we proved that for any Herm Mission
matrix it's expectation value is
real we also proved that the inner
product of a with itself is real real so
we have an equation that a real number
is equal to a real number time an igen
value well that means that the igen
value is
real or another way to write it is to
divide it by AA and the
ratio of two real numbers is certainly
real so the first statement is if we've
managed to succeed and
find a igen vector and an igen value of
a Herm Mission
Matrix the igen value will be real now
I'm going to tell you the secret the
secret is that if m is an
observable then the values of it that
you can measure when you do an
experiment are its igen values that
means the result of an experiment to
measure M will be one of the igen values
of the Matrix a M that's the
significance of igen values they're the
possible measurable
values of the observable that's
represented by
m me give you some examples some
very oh yes the lambdas the igen values
are the values that you
measure the igen vector that's
associated with that particular IG value
that igen Vector represents a
state where when you measure the
quantity M with certainty you get value
Lambda right so the igen values and the
igen vectors go together there are
certain States for any given observable
there are certain States and
certain uh certain states which when you
measure that particular observable you
will with probability one get a
particular answer and that answer is the
igen value so let's just do an an
example or
two um and the the easiest examples
involve diagonal
matrices here's a diagonal
matrix let's just give it some letters
M11 Zer just 2 by two is good enough for
us M22 there's a diagonal
matrix what are are its igen vectors
remember they're vectors which when you
multiply them by The Matrix you just get
the original Vector back times a
number okay I'll I'll just tell you the
answer there are two igen vectors of
this Matrix one of them has a one in the
upper place here let's check what does
this Matrix do when it multiplies this
Vector well we take the row multiply it
by the column that puts in the upper
place here
M11 but how about the lower Place 0 * 1
+ M22 * 0 just
zero but this Vector is just
M11 times 1
Z so you see what's happened the Matrix
times the vector gives you a number
times the original
Vector in other words in particular it
doesn't
change yeah it just gives you the back
the original Vector times a numerical
number in this case the numerical number
happens to be
M11 so the vector one is an igen Vector
of this Matrix with igen value
M11 there's another igen vector and the
other igen
Vector is to put a zero here
and a one
here let's see what we
get in the top place we get M11 * 0 + 0
* 1 is
0 and then we get 0 * 0 plus M22 * 1
M22 and that's just
M22 *
01 so we found another igen Vector
Matrix * vectoral number times the same
vector and this time the igen value is
M22 so the two
vectors
01 and one Z are both IG vectors but
with two different igen values M11 and
M22 you can see where this is going for
example if I'm interested in up down and
the spin of an
electron I might describe describe it by
a matrix with a with a one and a minus
one then the igen values would just be
one and minus
one the igen states would be 1
Zer that's a correct equation all right
so the state with the electron up is an
igen Vector of a certain observ able
which is represented by a
matrix and the
other igen Vector is
01 and that is equal to
minus
01 the minus comes from this minus sign
over here so the two the two states of
the electron up and down are igen
vectors of the spin operator the spin
operator which is usually called Sigma
3 it's his definition Sigma 3 is just
this there are igen vectors with two
different igen values and you see the
pattern that the value that you measure
either plus one or minus
one is the igen value the igen
vector is the state in which the igen
value is the desired measured quantity
any questions
it and in fact these are normalized
right room yeah rule we we normalize
vectors yes let me give you another
example which is less a little bit less
trivial oh incidentally if it were 3x3
or n byn matrices the same pattern would
be there that if the diagonal if the
matrices are diagonal then the diagonal
entries are the igen values and the
vectors are
just vectors with zeros everywhere
except in one place a one so you can
check that out for yourself experiment
around the diagonal uh Matrix
matrices let me give you one other
example the other example involves an
off diagonal
matrix these mat matrices incidentally
will play an important role uh in the
ones we're talking about but for the
time being they're just arbitrary
matrices it's Herm
Mission it has real diagonal elements
zero is a real number and the off
diagonal elements are complex conjugates
of each other one is its own complex
conjugate it also happens to be
symmetric uh but it's both Herm Mission
and
symmetric and now let's see if we can
find the igen vectors
better than to yeah
uh rather than to do a uh any algebra
I'm going to show you what they are and
then we'll see that they are igen
vectors the two igen vectors in this
case Okay now what's wrong with this
igen
Vector it's too big it's not normal ized
1^ 2 + 1 is 2 but here's a statement if
a vector is an igen Vector it doesn't
matter what its normalization is if you
double it or triple it or anything else
it's still an igen Vector but if you
wanted to normalize it you would write
one over square root of two 1 over < TK
of
two it doesn't really matter uh in
checking whether it's an Igan vector or
not but let's normalize it just uh to uh
to ourselves to always normalize vectors
right what is this Matrix times this
Vector all right we take the 01 and we
multiply it
by these two
uh elements and what do we get we get
zero time oh let me come on the side 0 *
1  two 1 over
s two and likewise in the
bottom we got back exactly the same
Vector so this is an igen
Vector of this operator with IG value +
one all right what
about 0 1 1 Zer can I find another igen
Vector yes I can the reason I can find
it is because they know the
answer but it's not it's it's not hard
to find it's not hard to find I just
want to illustrate the idea of igen
vectors another time I can tell you how
you would go about finding them but I
just want to illustrate it the other
possibility is 1 over < tk2 minus 1 / <
TK two in other words instead of having
the same element here and here we have
opposite sign let's check it
out 0 * this 0 1 * this is
minus - 1 / < TK of2
and then here we have 1/ < TK of 2 + 0
so we have 1/ < TK
two and that's the same thing as minus
the vector that we started with we have
a minus sign here and and the opposite
sign here it is
minus the original
Vector so we found another I vector and
this time the igen value is minus
one we found two IG
vectors with igen Value Plus One and
igen value minus
one I defy you to find any other igen
Vector there are
none there are none and that's a
theorem
and there are normal igen values or igen
vectors
right right right right you can always
multiply igen vector by a number and
it's still an igen Vector but no more uh
no more which are not just numerical
multiples of the same igen Vector
right all right I'm now going to prove a
fundamental theorem of quantum
mechanics very fundamental about Herm
Mission matrices am I going too
fast well if I am yell
out uh you call the spin
Matrix okay this one
say it
again yeah yeah yeah okay Sigma
3 and this is definition 1 one sorry 1 -
1 0 0 and it has igen value + one and
minus
one Sigma
1 is equal to this 1 1
Z I'll show you two interesting things
or well let's just to say one
interesting about both of these the
square of each one of these matrices
does everybody know how to square a
matrix how to multiply a matrix by
itself good the square of each of these
matrices is the same and it's just plus
one the square of this Matrix you just
Square the elements 1 squar and minus
one squar are both + one the square
Sigma 1 Let's Square Sigma 1 1 1 0 0 and
multiply it by 1 1 0
0 all right the first element in the
upper left hand corner is the inner
product this times this the 1 * the one
gives us a one then 0 * 1 + 1 * 0 0 1 *
1 + 0 * 0 no
sorry 1 * 0 + 0 * 1 is 0 and 1 * 1 + 0 *
0 is 1 so both Sigma 1^ s and sigma 3^
squ are both equal to one now that's
kind of an interesting fact notice that
it's also true of the igen values of the
matrices they were both plus and minus
one if a square of a thing is one it
stands the reason that it's uh that it's
either plus or minus one well for
matrices particular 2x2 matrices like
this but matrices in general if the
square of a
matrix is the unit Matrix matx this this
Matrix is called is the unit matrix it's
called
one all right it's just the unit Matrix
with ones on the
diagonal Sigma 3^
SAR Sigma
3^ squar is the same as Sigma 1^ SAR
equal to
1 and it's
not independent of the fact that the
square of each of it of the igen values
is equal to one It means that the
measured values that you can measure are
such that the square is equal to one and
it means that you can only measure plus
one or minus one there's one more Matrix
I'll write down and it's called Sigma
2 and it's equal to minus
I
I we will come back to the sigma matri
in fact we'll probably come back to them
tonight we found the igen vectors of
Sigma 1 and sigma 3 we have not yet
found the igen vectors of Sigma
2 and I will tell you in due time what
their significance is yeah yeah you can
see all this
geometrically very simple gec
interpretation
okay if you're going to say that then
tell us what this oh okay well I was
going to write something up I can put on
the internet tell me how
but basically uh if you look at the unit
vectors if you look at unit Vector well
think of E1 and E2 uh like 0 1 and 1 0o
as the unit vectors if you look at a
matrix if you look at the column vectors
those are the images of the unit vectors
I I know what you're saying so so so one
of them is is a reflect it's you're
interchanging E1 with
E2 that's called Sigma one right and so
the the diagonal is is
fixed and and also the anti- diagonal
fixed when when you're you're reflecting
in the in the main diagonal so the
normal to it is also reflect so so those
are I vectors those Direction
you got and then the uh that's the one
two things those are pointing in the
diagonal directions so they're fixed and
then the other one is um you're sending
uh you're keeping the E1 fixed and E2 is
going into into its negative so you're
reflecting in the X AIS so so the the
vertical Vector is an i Vector going
into its negative
right and also the squares of these
things if you apply them twice you come
back to where you exactly not so
completely obvious for this one but the
square of this one is also one yeah then
when I take the I out in front and I
have I * something very
obvious Sig 2 is also one not minus one
but one yeah they all have that
property they're all in that sense
they're similar also proves incidentally
that the igen values of Sigma 2 are also
plus and minus one doesn't tell us what
the igen victors are but it tells us
what the igen values
are all right let me prove to you now
the following interesting
theorem suppose and this
theorem is
significant highly
significant supposing you have an
observable
and it has more than one igen vector in
general will the number of igen vectors
that it has is usually equal to the
dimensionality of the Matrix it is the
dimensionality of the Matrix so if you
have n 3x3 matrices in their Herm
Mission they will typically have three
igen values and three igen
vectors 4x4 will have four igen vectors
and four igen values but here's a
theorem if I have
a
um a Herm Mission Matrix m
and it has two different igen values two
different igen
values that means that there's an igen
Vector
a with IG value Lambda
a and there is an IG Vector
B with a different
IG value Lambda b
b then if Lambda a and Lambda B are
different what it says is that a and b
will be orthogonal to each
other and before I prove it let me say
what it means what it means is that if
there is any observable
distinct quantity that you can measure
which will distinguish between two
different well two different distinctly
different possible measurable answers
that you can get for some obser
able then that's equivalent to saying
that the that the igen vectors remember
the igen vectors are the states in which
you definitely measure Lambda a the igen
vectors are the states where if you make
a measurement of M you will get Lambda a
b is the state in which if you measure M
you will definitely get Lambda B all
right these states which correspond to
distinctly different measurable
quantities did distinctly different
measurable values of the same
quantity they are orthogonal all right
that's that's the the basic idea is
orthogonal states are distinguishable
measurably distinct and you can
distinguish between them by measuring
appropriate uh uh
observables for example we already have
some
examples uh the two examples that we had
one of them was one and 01 these were
the two igen vectors of Sigma
3 notice that they're orthogonal because
they don't share any elements this times
this plus this times this is
zero the orthogonality is a thing that
tells you that in a unique experiment
you can distinguish between them you
distinguish between them by measuring
the
quantity which uh which is represented
by the Herm Mission operator that has
the too many words but uh but you get
the idea let me prove to
you that if this is so with two
different lambdas then A and B must be
orthogonal to each other and we do this
easily it's not very hard we just have
to juggle a few
definitions we first of all multiply
this equation the first equation on the
left by
B so we'll rewrite it then as B
M
A equals Lambda
a Time ba
a I've multiplied both sides by B by the
vector
B
okay going to do a similar thing here
I'm going to multiply both sides by a
and so we get
a
[Music]
MB equals Lambda B
times
AB but now I would like
to switch uh let's see so what do we
have to do next this always confuses me
yeah we have the two
equations now let's take
um this
equation
in yeah we want to conjugate one of
these equation equations we want to take
the complex conjugate of one of these
equations which one should we choose the
second
one right this is
b
m
a complex conjugated is what it
is remember since m is permission we
don't have to complex conjugate it
that's equal to Lambda B
Star time b a
okay now I forgot what to do next ah
yes yes
H yeah now we'll just now we'll just
comple conjugate everything uh oh did I
do
something
uh is
this did I forget to conjugate
something what are we doing we we a
sorry this is conjugated right yeah good
but before we do that let's complex what
I've done here is said if I interchange
let's
see ah this one this one if I
interchange A and
B and at the same time take the hermiss
conjugate of M which I don't have to do
because it's Herm Mission and take the
complex conjugate I get the comp I get
the complex conjugate of the right hand
side now just complic complex conjugate
the whole equation that means just throw
away the
star throw away the star now I have two
equations let's get rid of the middle
one
here one of them says b m AAL Lambda a *
ba the other one says b equals Lambda B
time
ba it will not surprise you that the
conclusion is there are two two possible
conclusions one conclusion is that
Lambda a equals Lambda the B but I told
you already I'm talking about two igen
values which are known to be
different so by assumption Lambda a and
Lambda B are not the same if Lambda a
and Lambda B are not the same there's
only one way this can be true in other
words and it's that ba is zero in other
words let's subtract these two equations
we subtract the two equations on the
left hand side we get zero on the right
hand side we get Lambda a minus Lambda B
times ba B
A if a product is equal to zero that
means one or the other factor is equal
to zero product of two things can only
be zero if one or the other factor is
equal to zero so one possibility is that
Lambda a is equal to Lambda B true this
is true it's a possibility but I
explicitly said let us cons consider two
different igen values two different
values of the
same uh observable if they're different
then Lambda a minus Lambda B is not
equal to zero and the only possibility
is that b and a are orthogonal to each
other that inner product of B with a is
equal to
zero so it follows for her Mission
matrices if I have two distinct igen
values I can immediately conclude that
these are orthogonal
vectors let's check it out for the igen
vectors of
um of Sigma 2 remember the where are the
igon vectors of Sigma 2 here they are
here they are right
[Music]
here no I'm sorry Sigma one is what I
meant Sigma
one let's check it out for Sigma 1
notice that the entry here are real and
we don't have to um we don't have to
complex conjugate
anything all the entries here are real
to take the inner product of two vectors
all of whose entries are real all we
have to do is take the product of the
first two entries sorry the product of
this entry with this entry and add to it
the product of this one with this one so
we get one overun of two * 1 < tk2
that's a half and then 1un 2 * - 1 of
two that's minus a half a half plus
minus a half is zero this Vector is
orthogonal to this Vector so there's an
example of the orthogonality of igen
vectors with different igen values for
Herm Mission
matrices right as I said the
significance of this is deep and it says
that whenever there is an observation
that you can do that will uniquely
distinguish between two possible states
of a system
system uh or two possible values of an
observable the states associated with
them are orthogonal to each other or you
can say it the other way if two states
are orthogonal it means that there
exists some measurement you can
do which will uniquely tell you which
one of the two is uh realized in your in
your uh in your
system okay so that's that's one of the
fundamental theorems of quantum
mechanics and let's take a little
break the igen vectors of Sigma 2 are so
that you can check them
yourself the two igen vectors of Sigma
2 the two igen vectors of Sigma
2 are
one I stick a one over < TK of two to
normalize it in front of it and the
other one is 1 minus I 1 overun
two one of them has igen value + one and
the other has igen value minus one all
right so you can check that yourself
it's a little exercise please do
it and you see that Sigma 1 Sigma 2 and
sigma 3 are all similar to each other
and that they have the same igen values
Plus plus one and minus
one they all square and give
one uh they have another interesting
property that we'll come to in in a
moment I
think um but let me tell you what their
physical meaning is they are observable
quantities and with respect and thinking
about the uh the electron
spin as I told you be first time or was
it the second time the electron Spin
classically and classical physics is
like a magnet it has a North Pole and a
South Pole and it's a pointer it points
along an axis if we were talking about
and it has what's called a magnetic
moment and that Magnetic Moment is a I I
hesitate to use the word Vector but the
kind of vector that points an ordinary
space I guess we call it a pointer huh
right right the Magnetic
Moment or we can call it the spin it's
the same apart from a numerical constant
the spin and the Magnetic Moment are the
same thing it's a v it's a it's a it's a
pointer in space right as such it has
components it has components in the
vertical axis for example this Vector
has a component which is about over here
in the vertical Direction it has a
component in the horizontal Direction
over here and a component over here in
the other horizontal Direction and those
components
characterize the point
pointer
okay they are measurable quantities for
a magnet you could decide to measure the
X component of the magnet of the uh of
the Magnetic Moment you could decide to
measure the Y component or you could
decide to measure the Z component you
might think classically you'd be right
that you could measure all three of them
simultaneously you could do an
experiment to measure all three of the
components of the Magnetic Moment
simultaneously and in that way figure
out exactly what the where the magnetic
uh moment is pointing all right let's
save that question whether you can
measure all of them simultaneously for
an electron or not but you can and the
answer is no but you can measure any one
of them the X component the Y component
or the Z component how do you do it
suppose I wanted to measure the X
component X is this way I put it in a
big magnetic field and I check whether
or not it uh it uh emits a
photon if it emits a photon then it had
one one component or the other component
and the only possible answers are minus
one and + one in other words you'll
either see a photon or you won't see a
photon so the
components of the electron spin have
only two possible values each of the
components the X component the Y
component and the Z component and what's
more we're going to see in a minute that
the component in any old direction if
you measure it will only have two
possible values now that's a little hard
to think about but uh but let me tell
you right now what Sigma 1 Sigma 2 and
sigma 3 are is they represent the
observable values of the
components of the electron spin along
the three axes of
space the three axes of ordinary
space I'll show you how that works and
how we can construct the component along
any direction in a moment but notice
that they do have sort of very similar
properties same igen values so if you
measure the possible values that you can
get in an experiment for Sigma 1 you get
one minus one for Sigma 3 you get one
and minus one for Sigma 2 you get one
and minus one that's all you can ever
get when you actually measure
them and we're going to see the same is
true along any axis
but before we do let me tell you the
last I think it's the last postulate of
quantum
mechanics and here's here's here is
the that's the probability
interpretation suppose you prepare a
system in a state particular State and
let's see let's call that
state B
somebody gave you an electron or
whatever it happens to be in a
particular Quantum State
B now there is some
observable let's call it m some
observable M that has an igen value
Lambda a which means that if you measure
M you can get the value Lambda
a or you may not get the value you may
get some other Lambda but if you measure
M you get one of its igen values and the
associated igen
Vector is
a commas between them just to indicate m
is an observable meaning to say it's a
hermiss operator Lambda a is one of the
possible values that you can measure and
the associated igen Vector is Lambda
a b is just any old State any Old State
whatever not particularly an igen state
of uh of M it could be or not all right
it's just any old arbitrary
State then we could ask the question if
the system is prepared in B and we
measure M what's the probability that
the answer will be Lambda
a okay Lambda a are the possible values
that you can
measure m is the thing you're
measuring and a is the igen vector of M
with value Lambda a the answer is that
the
probability is given by the
expression the inner product of a with
B times its complex conjugate one way uh
times its complex conjugate the easy way
to write the complex conjugate is just
to write it time ba
which is just the same as multiplying
this by its complex
conjugate remember that when you
multiply a number by its complex
conjugate you always get a real positive
number if a and b are normalized it's an
easy theorem to prove that this is less
than one less than or equal to one if a
and b are unit length the then the inner
product between them has a magnitude
less than
one so this number is always less than
or equal to one and it is the
probability it's the probability again
I'll I'll State what it is it's the
probability that if you start with an
arbitrary State a a system prepared in
an arbitrary State a and you measure the
measurable quantity
M this is the probability that you get
Lambda a
H sorry what did I say I say it
wrong oh
sorry okay let me say it again I thought
I said it the right way but I probably
said it wrong it's prepared in the state
B arbitrarily prepared in state
B then the probability that you measure
Lambda a will be the inner product
between b and a squared times it's
complex conjugate a real positive number
given by the
square or I call it the square but I
mean times the complex
conjugate of a with B okay that's the
probability now notice it's sort of
symmetric in A and B it is symmetric in
A and B but uh but uh for the moment
think of it asymmetrically you prepare
the system in a you you prepare the
system in b and you measure M and ask
what the probability for Lambda a is
okay that's the uh that's the basic
uh postulate of quantum mechanics always
assuming that all of your vectors are
normalized always assuming that your
vectors are normalized that your state B
is normalized and that the igen vector a
is
normalized is that
theine of the phase angle between
uh what is if these were if these were
real vectors in a real Vector space a
two two-dimensional Vector space it
would be the cosine of an angle no I
mean since they're both complex vectors
yeah they have an angle between them is
it the co is that equal to the of thatle
no no what do you mean they have a coine
angle between they no such concept okay
no no what is true is that uh
what is true is if these are just uh
ordinary threedimensional vectors real
vectors and ordinary three dimensions
that the dotproduct of two vectors two
unit vectors is equal to the cosine of
the angle between them so it's kind of
like the cosine of the angle but it's
not a real thing not real in general
this won't be real that's why we
multiply it by its complex
conjugate by the theorem you just Prov B
is
the vector of the different
value yeah good good good good good good
good excellent if B happens to be one of
the igen vectors of M with a different
igen
value then A and B are orthogonal and so
what it says is that if you prepare the
system in one igen vector corresponding
to a different igen value then the
probability that you get a is zero good
perfect uh so if you prepare it in in
one igen vector and you measure the
probability that you get a different
igen value is zero good so that's that's
part of the uh of the probabilistic
interpretation here and all it says is
if a if a quantity is definitely equal
to one thing it's surely not equal to
the other thing but uh but expressed in
terms of
um uh inner
products you have a that you at best
know that you have a certain certainty
of having prepared an State can you
still work with that this a little more
complicated but yes but uh but uh
um yeah we're going to we're going to do
many many such things but let's uh let's
this is the simplest of the things we
could
do and
um for the moment this is our basic
Quantum postulate of probabilities
Let's uh give an
example what's the probability let's
take the
case where Sigma 3 is equal to one let's
see let's say it this way we prepare we
prepare
B is equal to one
Z which means by the way that Sigma 3 is
equal to + one but now we're not going
to measure Sigma 3 we're going to
measure Sigma Sigma 1 we're going to
measure Sigma 1 and we're going to ask
what's the probability that when we
measure Sigma 1 that we get + one or
minus one is the case may be all right
so let's ask what what's the probability
that if we prepare here's the experiment
we prepare the system with the spin up
by putting it in a big magnetic field
pointing
upward and then we measure Sigma 1 which
is the component of the spin along the
x-axis what's the probability that we
get + one what's the probability that we
get minus1 you can guess but we'll work
it
out all right so what is
a a is an igen Vector of Sigma 1 with I
value let's say plus one so
a is equal to 1/ < tk2 1/ < tk2
what's the inner product between
these quick quick quick
quick 1/ s of two right one over Square
two what's the square of
it 12 so
AB is 1/ < TK two and times its complex
conjugate that's usually written this
way times its complex conjugate its
absolute value squared which is the same
is multiplied by its complex conjugate
is 1
12 so what this tells us is if we
prepare an electron in the upstate and
we measure the X component of spin we
have a probability 1/2 for getting
plus and it will also be true that we
will have probability 1/ half for
getting minus to see that what's the
igen vector that's associated with minus
one for Sigma for Sigma one we put a
minus in here
it doesn't change the
answer still
one2 okay so there's an
example and this is a characteristic
example you prepare a system in this
case the system is prepared with a spin
vertically up and it's measured in the
horizontal Direction let's do the
opposite we're going to get the same
answer oh let's uh yeah let's do let's
do we start B now this time we first
prepare the electron
horizontally and we measure the vertical
component it's going to be the same in a
product the horizontal this time B this
we've just all we've done is interchange
b and
a I forgot which was which now b and
a we've prepared the system with its
spin pointing with its X component
positive and we measured the Z component
it's just exactly the same thing
12 let's do a more complicated case I've
told you what the igen vectors of Sigma
2 are so let's ask the most complicated
question we can
ask what's the
probability that if we prepare the
state with Sigma 1 equal positive one
that means B is equal to 1/ > two 1
overun
two and this time we measure Sigma 2 not
Sigma 3 but Sigma 2 so this time B is
one of the two igen vectors of Sigma
2 let's take this
one
[Music]
one over < TK two I over < TK two
sorry this is a now this is
a a the igen vector of Sigma 2 so we
start with a spin pointing along the
x-axis and we measure it along the Y
AIS we start with it pointing along the
x axis that's an igen Vector of Sigma 1
or along the one axis and now we measure
it along the two axxis Okay can somebody
compute the inner product of these two I
think I can
can the inner product of these two we
first of all have to complex conjugate
so don't forget the complex conjugate
but it's 1 over the < TK of 2 * 1 < TK
of two is
12 and then
plus but we have to complex conjugate so
that means
minus
I over two 1 of two * 1 of two is 12
with an i this is the inner product of a
with
B I don't know if it's a with b or B
with a but it doesn't matter okay what's
the complex conjugate of this with
itself let's work it out we have to
multiply it by 1 over 2+ I /
2 quick answer not
one okay the imaginary Parts cancel we
have a 1/2 * a 1/2 with an i and then we
have a minus 1/2 * a 1/2 with a minus I
so the imaginary Parts cancel the real
parts are 1 12 * 1/2 is 1 14 plus one
142 okay so we see if we the way to say
this now is if we line up the the spin
in any direction by a strong magnetic
field and then we measure the spin in a
perpendicular direction we have a half
prob in any in fact in any perpendicular
direction we have a probability of a
half that it's this way and a half that
it's this way okay so any polariz it's
called the spin polarization any spin
state if we start it out with a strong
magnetic field and freeze it into some
direction if we then remove the magnetic
field and measure an orthogonal
component to spin it will have equal
probability of being up and
down what about the components of spin
in some arbitrary
Direction let's discuss the components
of spin along some other axis are we
maybe it's a good time to stop now and
uh well let's let's let's do
it and I promise to do this again
yeah regarding orthogonal and this this
case versus classical if you have two
two vectors that are 90° of part you
would say are we talking about vectors
or pointers uh pointers they're 90° AP
part we often say
this and the projection of one and the
other equals zero however okay good good
good good good okay so let's not so
right so we have to we have to
distinguish uh vectors from
pointers right so here we have a
situation where we have where we have a
pointer which has been forced to point
in some direction and we measure the
pointiness in a what's called
perpendicular Direction all right let's
not all right good or let's just say
yeah okay good good or better yet let's
look at the igen vector which
corresponds to the pointiness plus one
in the X Direction and compare it with
the igen vector that corresponds with
the pointiness in another Direction
they're not orthogonal igen vectors
they're not orthogonal vectors in the in
this
sense yeah yeah right comes out to 1/2
instead of zero right
good what is the thing which has zero
probability of pointing up like
this yeah the one that's pointing down
the one that's pointing down
in this sense is orthogonal to the one
pointing up so we have to so let's use
the word perpendicular to mean ordinary
space an orthogonal okay here's our our
vocabulary pointers instead of
vectors vectors mean States pointers
mean pointers orthogonality means States
being orthogonal being distinctly
different from each other measurably
different and perpendicular means
perpendicular at 90 degrees in ordinary
space
okay
good independent means something a
little
different independent doesn't mean
perpendicular so let's stick with the
word
in
no uh independent simply means it's not
pointing in the same
direction and the set of vect there's a
concept of Independence linear
independence with but uh which is not
which is different than orthogon Mutual
orthogonality uh so in Independence and
orthogonality are quite
different uh or linear Independence
anyway okay now let's let's come to
classical
pointers I'm interested in something new
I'm interested now in the component of
the pointer along an arbitrary Direction
along an arbitrary Direction in real
space what direction let's pick a
Direction how do we pick a direction we
pick a direction by picking a set of
components of a unit Vector we take a
unit vector and pick a set of components
in let's call let's call the unit vect
sorry unit pointer my
goodness a unit pointer we take a unit
pointer now this is in real
three-dimensional space
uh
one 2 3 one is the same as x two is the
same as y three is the same as Z same
thing XYZ and now I pick some arbitrary
pointer so some arbitrary
pointer this
pointing along that
direction and let's take it to be a unit
Vector which means it's one unit in
length it's described by a set of three
components the sums of the squares of
the components have to add up to one but
here are the three components let's call
this Vector n and a unit Vector is
usually described by putting a little
hat over it like that in hat means a
unit Vector this is a standard notation
for a unit Vector a unit pointer my
goodness please correct me don't allow
me to do that a unit pointer is
indicated by a little hat and it has a
set of components the components are n x
n y and n z or N1 N2 and
N3 those are the
components and they're
basically this component this component
and this component you add them up and
you get the pointer that's point
pointing in some arbitrary
Direction okay these are the
components of the
pointer now what what about the
component of the spin along the
direction n how do we calculate
that
that the component of the spin or the
component of the spin pointer along the
arbitrary Direction in is given let's
call it the spin let's now we're
thinking classically we're thinking
about a classical magnetic uh moment a
classical
spin the dot product sigma.
n is the component of Sigma along the
direction of n that's what a dotproduct
is it's the component of one vector
along the axis of another Vector sorry
pointer
what is sigma. n it's the first
component or the X component call it
Sigma 1 time
N1 plus Sigma
2 *
N2 plus sigma3 time
N3 well this gives us an interesting
candidate in the quantum mechanics for
the operator which is the component of
spin along a direction
n namely we take the operator Sigma 1
multiply it by N1 add to it the operator
Sigma 2 * N2 add to it the operator
Sigma 3 and multiply it by N3 that's a
candidate and it is it is the correct
candidate which we can call sigma. n but
it's an operator why is it an operator
the ends are numbers they're just
numeric numbers that multiply uh here
Sigma are
matrices if we multiply a matrix by a
number we just multiply all the entries
by the same number and then we add them
up we can write this down actually given
Three N N1 N2 and N3 we can add them up
let's do it N1 * Sigma 1 what's Sigma 1
Sigma 1 is 1 one and if I multiply it by
N1 it looks like this
that's Sigma 1 *
N1 what about Sigma 2 * N2 well Sigma 2
is - I I and now we multiply it by
N2 Sigma 3 *
N3 we take N3 which is 1 - one and we
multiply LLY it by N3 so that's just N3
N3 0
0 now we add them up and what do we
get on the diagonal these have no
diagonal elements this has diagonal so
we get
N3
N3 minus
N3 we get
N1 minus I N2
and
[Music]
N1 plus I
N2 these are three three components N1
N2 and N3 the sums of the squares should
be equal to one because it's a unit
vector and here is the operator that
corresponds to measuring the components
of spin along the direction in so what's
the experiment the
experiment is we take an electron on and
we put it in the magnetic field pointing
along the end direction and we see what
we get up or down this is the operator
that corresponds to that
N3 on diagonal minus N3 N1 minus I N2 is
this her Mission yes it's her Mission
real real and this one's the complex
conjugate of this so it's her
mission is it it Square equal to
one what's
that any
un well I I don't expect you to be able
to see it off hand so what I'm going to
do is I'm going
to show you an important property and
let you check it
yourself this is an important property
of these Sigma matrices one that you can
check but I'll derive it I I I'll derive
its importance and then allow you to
check it uh by
yourself let's take this Sigma 1 plus
Sigma 2 Sigma 1 N1 plus Sigma 2 N2 plus
Sigma 3 N3 leave it in this form not in
this form leave it in this form and
square it what do we get well let's
let's write it out Sigma 1 N1 plus Sigma
2 n 2 + Sigma 3
N3 times Sigma 1 N1 plus Sigma 2 N2 plus
Sigma 3 N3 let's multiply we're going to
get a whole slew of terms all right the
first terms first set of terms are going
to be things like Sigma 1^ 2 * N1 2 when
I multiply this out I'll get Sig what's
Sigma 1
squ one so from the from from the n1^ 2
Sigma 1^ 2 terms we get n1^ 2
right what about from the sigma 2 time
Sigma 2
term plus N2 2 what about from the sigma
3 N3 term plus n3^
s but what's that that's one all right
now let's look at Sigma let's look at
the thing which multiplies N1 * N2
here's the thing which is going to
multiply N1 *
N2 N1 N2 and what's it going to contain
it's going to contain Sigma 1 Sigma 2
but then there's another term like that
which is Sigma 2 Sigma
1 all right you get one term which is
Sigma 1 on the left Sigma 2 on the right
and the other term has Sigma 2 on the
left Sigma 1 on the right
why do I bother writing Sigma 1 Sigma 2
and sigma 2 and sigma 1 instead of just
calling them both Sigma 1 Sigma
2 because when you multiply
matrices the order
counts the order counts when you
multiply
matrices matrices in general have
different products when you multiply
them in different
orders that the technical term is that
they don't
commute so it's important that these
things all when you multiply them by
cells they give you one unit Matrix the
identity Matrix yeah these are these
each of the square of these gives the
Iden I know but you just kind to prove
that for the for the
sigma we're going to prove that
right then then we
have n 2 N3 * Sigma 2 Sigma 3 plus Sigma
3 Sigma 2 and then another term similar
which is N1 *
N3 all right well this adds up to
one which means the unit Matrix this is
the unit
Matrix
one what's this doing here this is bad
we don't want that there we want the
square of the component of the spin in
any direction to be the same as in every
other direction there's nothing special
about any of these Direction
well try it out multiply let's multiply
uh let's multiply Sig ah this you go
home and do
yourself prove to yourself that Sigma 1
* Sigma 2 is the opposite is the
negative of Sigma 2 * Sigma one
h no no no no no they anticommute this
is a special property they anti-c
commute which is to say that when you
change the order it changes their sign
this is something to check you sit down
and do it
numerically Sigma 1 Sigma 2 plus Sigma 2
Sigma 1 is
zero Sigma 2 Sigma 3 plus Sigma 3 Sigma
2 is zero let's we have five minutes we
have three minutes let's do one case one
case for fun let's
see
uh let's
do I avoid imaginary numbers by doing
Sigma 1 and sigma 3 Sigma 1 * Sigma 3
what's that that's equal to 1 1 0 0 Time
1 0 0 - 1 and that's equal to let's
see uh this time this is
zero this times this is minus one this
time this is
one and this times this is zero did I
get that right
I think I did okay now let's do it the
other way 1 0 0 - one 0 1 1
0 all right in the first element 1 * 0 +
0 * 1 that's 0o
again but now let's go to 1 * 1 is
1 and now we go down to this corner
that's 0 * 0 -
1 0 so you notice when you multiply them
in opposite
order you get exactly the same thing
except for a minus sign when you add
these Sigma 1 Sigma 3 and sigma 3 Sigma
1 add them together you get
zero same is true for Sigma 1 Sigma 2
and sigma 2 Sigma 3 so these are zero
so what have we learned we've learned
that with this particular choice of
matrices the
square of any component of Sigma along
any axis any axis whatever is one that
means the igen
values of such a matrix are plus and
minus
one so any Matrix where did I write it I
had it written
down here it is
the igen values of any Matrix of this
form are plus or minus one this will'll
check next time but what it says is the
possible measurable values of the spin
along any axis of plus or minus one okay
this is a very weird thing in quantum
mechanics you can only get plus or minus
one if you measure it along any
axis right but then take another axis
you can also only get plus or minus one
plus or minus one
the it's the probabilities which reflect
whether two ends we'll come to it next
time that's enough for this time uh I
probably saturated you you I've
certainly saturated myself
[Music]
yeah the preceding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu